Downtown Progress 025
People's Archive, MLK Library
Downtown Progress Records
1960-1977
People's Archive, MLK Library
Downtown Progress
National Capital Downtown Committee (Washington, D.C.)
025
51.5 Linear feet
104 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Action Plan, 1 linear ft. (1961-1968) This series provides background research, drafts, internal memoranda, sketches, meeting notes, and other materials regarding early planning resulting in the Action Plan for Downtown Progress prepared in 1962. Most notable is a discussion draft (not for publication) of the Plan, a joint report by the Washington Post and the Washington Star about the Plan, "Assumptions, Findings and Objectives" for the sketch plan, and the final version of the Plan. The Action Plan was an official publication of the Potomac Valley Chapter, American Institute of Architects. It also contains advisory committee meeting notes and membership lists as well as notes, street diagrams, maps, photographs, and sketches of squares in downtown. Folders are arranged chronologically followed by materials about the advisory committee and then maps and sketches. Series 2: Board of Directors, 1.25 linear ft. (1960-1977) The series contains correspondence, reports, internal memoranda, meeting minutes, agendas, testimony and other information used to prepare for the Board of Directors meetings. The folders are arranged chronologically. Series 3: Annual Membership and Board of Directors Meeting, 2.5 linear ft. (1960-1969) The series contains materials regarding the annual membership and Board of Directors meeting. It includes Board of Directors meeting minutes, committee reports, statements issued at annual meetings, meeting agendas, photographs, correspondence, and internal memoranda gathered or prepared for the meeting. The folders are arranged chronologically. Series 4: Annual Reports, .50 linear ft. (1971-1977) The series contains work folders for Downtown Progress' annual reports. The folders include the final annual report, "memoranda of contact", internal memoranda, correspondence, and notes. The folders are arranged chronologically. Series 5: Committee Files, 9.5 linear ft. (1964-1977) This series contains standing and ad hoc committee files. Included are committee reports, meeting agendas and minutes, notes, correspondence, and internal memoranda regarding the committees' work. Committees included in the series are budget review; development, environment, and preservation; executive; facilities; housing and relocation; legislative; nominating, planning, urban renewal, and relocation; transportation and services; zoning and codes. The folders are arranged alphabetically by name of committee with general files first. Series 6: General Office Files, 8.5 linear ft. (ca. 1960-1977) This series consists of subject files maintained in Downtown Progress' offices to track major projects and topics of interest. It includes correspondence, internal memoranda, forms to track telephone calls and meetings, reports, handwritten notes, maps, diagrams, testimony, and legislation. It covers a variety of topics affecting downtown development, including a rezoning study, historic landmark status, a proposed sports arena/convention and civic center, national visitors center at Union Station, transportation issues, Design and Feasibility studies, and the Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation. It also contains background materials, public testimony and statements, reports, and internal memoranda/correspondence regarding U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development's (HUD) Neighborhood Development Programs for the District proposed by the National Capital Planning Commission (NCPC) beginning in the 1970s, and information about squares slated for development. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title. Series 7: Legal Documents, 1.75 linear ft. (1971-1977) The series primarily contains pleadings in a case brought by Businessmen Against Second Year Action Plan (BASYAP) to stop proposed condemnation and redevelopment for certain sections of the downtown urban renewal area. The plaintiffs included 126 downtown business people affected by the Plan who sued the Redevelopment Land Agency, Downtown Progress, NCPC, the City Government, and others in federal court to stop the Plan. It also contains pleadings regarding a case brought against Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (WMATA) for refusal to install a second elevator at the Gallery Place Metro stop in compliance with handicap access laws in the late 1970s. Series 8: Images, 5.25 linear ft. (ca. 1960-1970) The series contains photographs, slides and sketches of buildings and street scenes in the Downtown Progress corridor. It is further divided into subseries as follows: Subseries 1: Photographs and Sketches, 1.5 cu. ft. (ca. 1960s) Contains photographs from the 1960s before development began in the downtown area as well as a number of photographs of F Street stores and streetscapes. It also contains sketches of buildings, streets, and walkways proposed for the new downtown urban renewal area. Subseries 2: Slides, 3.75 linear ft. (ca. 1960-1970s) Consists primarily of slides of buildings located within squares 213-491 and 514-631. They are arranged by address and square. It also contains some slides of F Street stores and streetscapes.
Biographical / Historical
Downtown Progress, originally known as the National Capital Downtown Committee, was a non-profit organization of businesspeople formed in 1959 to revitalize the area from the United States Capitol to the White House. The downtown urban renewal area was bounded by 5th and 15th Streets NW, and Pennsylvania Avenue to Massachusetts Avenue NW. Among projects promoted by Downtown Progress were the construction of the Metro, the Martian Luther King Jr. Memorial Library, and the F Street Mall. The group also supported the preservation efforts of Ford's Theatre, the Old Patent Office, Old Post Office and the Willard Hotel. The organization was officially disbanded in 1977 and turned into a public sector of the government known as the National Capital Planning Commission.
Custodial History
The collection was donated to the Library by Knox Banner, Exective Director of Downtown Progress in May 1977.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, meeting minutes, committee reports, memoranda, legal papers, and general office files of Downtown Progress. Also included are photographs, sketches, maps, architectural drawings, street diagrams, and slides of buildings and streetscapes located in the downtown urban renewal area of Washington, D.C.
Urban renewal; Neighborhoods; Nonprofit organizations; Businesspeople; Correspondence; Minutes (Records); Organizational Records; Legal documents; Photographs; Slides (Photography); Maps; Downtown (Washington, D.C.)
- Series 1: Action Plan, 1961-1968
  Scope and Contents
  This series provides background research, drafts, internal memoranda, sketches, meeting notes, and other materials regarding early planning which resulted in the Action Plan for Downtown Progress prepared in 1962. Most notably, it includes a discussion draft (not for publication) of the Plan, a joint report by the Washington Post and Star about the Plan, "Assumptions, Findings and Objectives" for the sketch plan, and the final version of the Plan.. The Action Plan was an official publication of the Potomac Valley Chapter, American Institute of Architects. It also contains advisory committee meeting notes and membership lists as well as notes, street diagrams, maps, photographs, and sketches of squares in downtown. Folders are arranged chronologically followed by materials about the advisory committee and then maps and sketches.
  The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - "Development of Washington and Its Central City" by Paul D. Spreiregen, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "L'Enfant's Plan for Washington" by Paul D. Spreiregen, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Assumptions, Findings and Objectives, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Churches study, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Background, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sketch Plan for Action Plan, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Report and Sketch Plan for Revitalization, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Discussion draft, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Discussion draft with annotations, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Action Plan comments, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Presentation Material at annual meeting, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Statements re studies, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Studies by consultants, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Action Plan for Downtown, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspapers (Post and Star) report on Plan, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Advisory committee, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Advisory committee, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Maps and sketches, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Square diagrams, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Square diagrams, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Urban renewal base map, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Board of Directors, 1975-1977
  The series contains correspondence, reports, internal memoranda, meeting minutes, agendas, testimony and other information used to prepare for the Board of Directors meetings. The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Untitled, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1961-1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Annual Membership and Board of Directors Meeting, 1960-1969
  The series contains materials regarding the annual membership and board of directors meeting. It includes board of directors meeting minutes, committee reports, statements issued at annual meetings, meeting agendas, photographs, correspondence, and internal memoranda gathered or prepared for the meeting. The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Untitled, 1961-1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1969-73 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1974-1975 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1975-1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Series 4: Annual Reports, 1971-1977
  The series contains work folders for Downtown Progress' annual reports. The folders include the final annual report, "memoranda of contact", internal memoranda, correspondence, and notes. The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - General correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Budget and Review, 1964-1977 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Series 5: Committee Files, 1964-1977
  This series contains standing and ad hoc committee files. Included are committee reports, meeting agendas and minutes, notes, correspondence, and internal memoranda regarding the committees' work. Committees included in the series are budget review; development, environment, and preservation; executive; facilities; housing and relocation; legislative; nominating, planning, urban renewal, and relocation; transportation and services; zoning and codes. The folders are arranged alphabetically by name of committee with general files first.
  - General Correspondence, 1971-72 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Budget and Review, 1964-1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Development, Environment, Preservation, 1963-1977 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1961-1962 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1963-1964 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1965-1966 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1970 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1971 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1972-1973 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1974, Parts 1 & 2 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1975, Part 1 of 2 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Executive, 1974, Parts 1 & 2 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Executive, 1975, Part 2 of 2 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Executive, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Executive, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Facilities, 1960-1977 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Housing and Relocation, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Legislative, 1964-1971 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Legislative, 1964-1971 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Nominating, 1971-1977 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Planning and urban renewal, 1962-1969 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Planning and urban renewal, 1970-1977 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Transportation and services, 1962-1965 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Transportation and services, 1966-1968 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Transportation and services, 1970-1976 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Zoning and codes, 1962-1972 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Zoning and codes, 1973-1977 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Mailing, 1963-1973 (Box 37, Folder 2)
- Series 6: General Office Files, ca. 1960-1977
  This series consists of subject files maintained in Downtown Progress' offices to track major projects and topics of interest. It includes correspondence, internal memoranda, forms to track telephone calls and meetings, reports, handwritten notes, maps, diagrams, testimony, and legislation. It covers a variety of topics affecting downtown development, including a rezoning study, historic landmark status, a proposed sports arena/convention and civic center, national visitors center at Union Station, transportation issues, Design and Feasibility studies, and the Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation. It also contains background materials, public testimony and statements, reports, and internal memoranda/correspondence regarding HUD's Neighborhood Development Programs for the District proposed by the National Capital Planning Commission (NCPC) beginning in 1970s and information about squares slated for development. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Assessed Valuation by blocks, 1960-1965 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Biographical data-R. Gray, Undated (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Chinese Community, 1971-1977 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Cleveland Park, Undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Developers, 1975-1977 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Developers, 1975-1977 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Developers, 1975-1977 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Development, 1973-1977 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Development, 1973-1977 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Design and Feasibility Study - General, Undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Design and Feasibility Study - Combined use office/retail (Squares 344/345), 1962-1963 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Design and Feasibility Study - Center leg freeway and air rights, 1964 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Design and Feasibility Study - Center leg freeway and air rights, 1964 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Development, 1970-1977 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Development, 1970-1977 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Development, 1972-1973 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Development Bank, 1972-1974 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Downtown Development Corporation, 1970-74 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Downtown Design and Development Program, 1967-1971 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Downtown Design and Development Program, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Downtown Feasibility Survey - Manufacturing/Wholesale study, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Downtown report, Undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Downtown structures, Undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Dupont Circle, Undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Dupont Circle property owners, Undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Employment studies, 1966-1967 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Employee Survey, 1960-1971 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Economic incentives task force, 1979 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Federal Triangle, 1979 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Fortune 500, 1972-1974 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Format, Undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Furniture stores, Undated (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Historic landmarks, 1963-1964 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Historic landmarks, 1978 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Historic landmark legislation, 1978 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Historic Preservation - American Institute of Planners conference, 1979 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Historic preservation - Newsclippings, Undated (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Historic preservation - Economic incentives, Undated (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Historic Preservation, Undated (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Home survey, Undated (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - James Creek-Buzzard Point, Undated (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - J-51, Undated (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Lincoln Place, Undated (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Maps, Undated (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Boxes 48, Undated (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Maps, Undated (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Square East, Undated (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Neighborhood Development Plan #3, Undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood Development Plan #4, 1970-74 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Neighborhood Development Plan #4, 1970-74 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood Development Plan #5, 1974 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood Development Plan, 1971-1977 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - National Visitors Center, 1960-1978 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - National Visitors Center, 1960-1978 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - National Visitors Center, Undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Nightlife study, Undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Pedestrian survey, Undated (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Pedestrians, Undated (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, 1973 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, 1973 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, 1973 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, 1974 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Performing Arts, 1962 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Permit, 1975 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Public and Private development draft, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Radio and T.V. spots, 1974-1977 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Speeches and remarks, Undated (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Sports Arena/Convention and Civic Center, 1963-1968 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Boxes 62-66, Undated (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Sports Arena/Convention and Civic Center, 1970-1977 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - SA/CC, 1977-1978 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Street vending, 1971-1974 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Turner Construction Company EEO Plan, 1973 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Transportation and highways, 1970-71 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Transportation, Undated (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Union Station, Undated (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Visitors Survey, 1960 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - YMCA site information, 1977-1978 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Sports Arena/Convention Center, Undated (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Zoning, 1958-1979 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Zoning, 1958-1979 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Zoning, 1958-1979 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - Zoning, 1958-1979 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - Square 214-250, Undated (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Squares 251-284, Undated (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Squares 285-321, Undated (Box 75, Folder 1)
  - Squares 322-377, Undated (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Squares 379-429, Undated (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Squares 451-491, Undated (Box 78, Folder 1)
  - Squares 514-562, Undated (Box 79, Folder 1)
  - Squares 564-630, Undated (Box 80, Folder 1)
- Series 7: Legal Documents, 1971-1977
  The series primarily contains pleadings in a case brought by Businessmen Against Second Year Action Plan (BASYAP) to stop proposed condemnation and redevelopment for certain sections of the downtown urban renewal area. The plaintiffs included 126 downtown businessman affected by the Plan who sued the Redevelopment Land Agency, Downtown Progress, NCPC, the City Government, and others in federal court to stop the Plan. It also contains pleadings regarding a case brought against WMATA for refusal to install a second elevator at the Gallery Place Metro stop in compliance with handicap access laws in the late 1970s.
  - Gallery Place suit, Undated (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - WMATA, Undated (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Businessmen Against Second Year Action Plan (BASYAP), 1970-1971 (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - BASYAP NDP#3, 1969-1972 (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - BASYAP, 1970-1971 (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - BASYAP, 1976-1977 (Box 84, Folder 1)
- Series 8: Images, ca. 1960-1970
  The series contains photographs, slides and sketches of buildings and street scenes in the Downtown Progress corridor.
  - Subseries 1: Photographs and Sketches, ca. 1960s
    Contains photographs from the 1960s before development began in the downtown area as well as a number of photographs of F Street stores and streetscapes. It also contains sketches of buildings, streets, and walkways proposed for the new downtown urban renewal area.
    - Photographs, 1960s (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 1960s (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - Sketches, 1960s (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of F Street, Undated (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Slides, ca. 1960-1970s
    Consists primarily of slides of buildings located within squares 213-491 and 514-631. They are arranged by address and square. It also contains some slides of F Street stores and streetscapes.
    - Slides of F Street, Undated (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Squares 213-223, Undated (Box 90, Folder 1)
    - Squares 224-253, Undated (Box 91, Folder 1)
    - Squares 254-290, Undated (Box 92, Folder 1)
    - Squares 291-346, Undated (Box 93, Folder 1)
    - Squares 347-401, Undated (Box 94, Folder 1)
    - Squares 402-428, Undated (Box 95, Folder 1)
    - Squares 429-458, Undated (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Squares 459-491, Undated (Box 97, Folder 1)
    - Squares 514-529, Undated (Box 98, Folder 1)
    - Squares 530-631, Undated (Box 99, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified slides, Undated (Box 100, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified slides, Undated (Box 101, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified slides, Undated (Box 102, Folder 1)